welcome to our lecture on VLSI, Very Large Scale Integration we're going to lay out some circuits
using basically a paint program to build millions of transistors and use photolithography so when i was
in master's degree long time ago i used a tool called magic this was an open source VLSI layout
tool that's created at berkeley in 1983 and it's very very popular because it's free and if you
google things like how to build a VLSI NAND gate you will see lots and lots of magic demonstrations
on youtube i decided not to have you use magic it's just a little too much it's really a powerful
and sophisticated tool so what i did was build little simple circuit layout tools so all my
tools are built for this course they're not real layout tools you can't really do layout with them
all i care about is the learning objectives in this course they run in the browser don't require
any installation but don't push them too hard if you build super complex circuits that might be
valid circuits my emulators will fall apart just do the homework in them play in them have a good
time but don't try to get too sophisticated if you really want to install more sophisticated
emulators either you know on your computer or online well you have fun with that this is just
to get you started so the first thing we're going to talk about is how to map the VLSI
CMOS NOT so we have a NOT gate the abstraction zero goes to one one goes to zero and we have
a CMOS layout where we have an a pMOS transistor at the top and an nMOS transistor at the bottom
we've gone through that in some detail and on the right is the VLSI layout for that so let's talk a
little bit about what it takes to do VLSI layout so the mystic program that i wrote for you does
painting on a grid and you can paint various things you can paint multiple things in one little
grid cell like the blue light blue in this case going across the top is metal and the pink is
polysilicon and the green is n-doped silicon and the orange is p-doped silicon and you lay these out
by simply drawing them and you'll see that there's also a voltage source on the metal in the top
example now these are not necessarily connected they can pass by each other and in particular
metal passes by everything unless you connect it and you connect it by punching a little hole in
it using what's called a via and it's a vertical net connector between the layers so you can see
in the top diagram that the polysilicon n-doped silicon and p-doped silicon does not have any
positive charge that's because they're not really connected to the metal but if you put vias at each
of the connections then the positive charge moves from the metal to the poly silicon n-doped silicon
and p-doped silicon now to make a transistor it takes polysilicon plus n-doped or p-doped silicon
and you create the transistor whether it's an NMOS transistor or PMOS transistor when you cross
polysilicon crosses n-doped it makes an NMOS transistor and when polysilicon crosses p-doped
it produces a PMOS transistor so if we look we see metal across the top we see a vertical n-doped
and a vertical p-doped coming down with a via and then we have a horizontal polysilicon with a plus
charge on it and at the moment that it's crossing the green or the n-doped it causes a transistor
and given that that is an NMOS transistor when positive voltage is transmitted to through it
then it copies the voltage through it the PMOS on the other hand when it's presented with a one
basically it blocks and so you can see the positive voltage flowing down the bound to PMOS
but stopping at the transistor and so these overlaps between the n-doped and p-doped and the
polysilicon are the transistors and if you look at the bottom one you see the exact same circuit
that has a zero or negative on it and you see that the NMOS transistor is blocking and the PMOS
transistor is conducting now the layout here my little layout is greatly simplified and my
circuit emulation is greatly simplified it's good enough to do not gates and NAND gates and NOR gates
and if you're really interested you can ask AI to explain the differences between VLSI layout and
actual manufacturing layout because there's actual differences in the construction for
example here you can draw it on my system but you're not supposed to overlap n and p
dope silicon due to manufacturing let me tell you but you want to connect them
you throw a little piece of metal and a couple of vias and then you can connect them so if you're
using the circuit simulation software you can turn on this layer mode where you point at a layer and
it shows the layers from top to bottom and again this isn't perfectly right but you can see like
on the left you can see a polysilicon and a p-doped silicon and you see them connect
and that makes a PMOS transistor you can see that on the on the layer chart where the p and
the poly are touching and that's where the transistor is being created and then if you look on the right
where you have the metal and the p-doped silicon they are connected via a via and you can think of
the via as a little hole that's drilled through all the layers with a little kind of bit of metal
poured in so they're all actually connected and so that via is how the metal the positive charge
goes from the metal at the top to the p-doped silicon going down vertically so here is a
CMOS knot and you you can see that it creates a PMOS transistor at the top and an NMOS
transistor at the bottom it uses metal to move the voltages around and via is to connect the
various silicon layers at the right point and so you see the input on the right on the left side
is a zero and then goes to the two transistors the PMOS at the top and the NMOS at the bottom
and you can see one of them in the case of the input zero the NMOS at the bottom is non-conducting
and so the ground is not going to output but the top PMOS transistor is conducting so the positive
is is then copied to the output just like in the circuits we were looking at before
and if you switch the input to one then the PMOS transistor at the top stops conducting
and the NMOS transistor at the bottom starts conducting and so the the negative the ground that's
coming up from the bottom is conducted through the NMOS transistor to the output and so now
we have a knot and i won't go through everything about this but you can then extend this to make
things more complex than not and so we talked a little bit about nan gates nan gates have
two PMOS transistors at the top and two NMOS transistors at the bottom it's kind of like
kind of half parallel half in series not gate and and if you trace the little picture you can see
that i've i've created that you can see there's four transistors and i will do a demonstration
where it actually reads the whole circuit so you can watch it in slow motion but you can see the
voltage at the top that's the voltage in the ground at the bottom and you can see the voltage
coming down through some vias to some p-doped silicon you can see the two inputs and you can
see them in this case they're both one and they are in effect being transported you see it a place
where the the second input is being connected to polysilicon then it's going over top of a
different polysilicon then it is going on top of a p-doped silicon and then it is connecting to a
horizontal polysilicon so that it can be make a transistor for the other of the PMOS transistors
that make the nan gate up now if we look at the bottom the bottom is thing where we're deciding
whether negative is going out or not and in this case because they're both positive there's two
NMOS transistors you can see the the green n-doped silicon going up and because both inputs are
positive both of those transistors are transmitting and so what's being copied to output is the
negative from ground so if we switch to a different row in the truth table a of zero and b of one
we can see how the nan gate changes a little bit right so the zero goes and makes it so that the
p plus is conducting at the top that's conducting a plus down then that is going to make the output
be plus and then you watch that same ground that same zero go down to the top NMOS transistor and
then that blocks that NMOS transistor that keeps ground from flowing out and so it's you can trace
all of the traces and all the connections and all the vias and see there's transistors and connections
and they basically implement the circuit diagram of the nand this has been a long series of lectures
talking about semiconductors we started about tubes and how do tubes and transistors need to
be tuned for digital applications where they have sort of the the quick transition at the one third
point for digital applications again these are analog devices although we want to treat them and
think of them as digital then we go from transistors to gates which makes it so that we can think
digital even though the underlying thing is an analog transistor then we watch the evolution of
transistor technology from PMOS to NMOS and then currently CMOS and how photolithography
makes it so we can put more and more transistors on the chip over time and manufacturing has gotten
better over time and we did a really brief introduction to how to design vlsi design chips
using vlsi layout tools so i hope you found that interesting up next we're going to switch from
transistors to pure digital logic and design much more sophisticated circuits
using exclusively digital logic and gates